<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml'>

<h2>News and current status</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://freshmeat.net/branches/39759/">Software release announcements</a></li>
<li><a href="support.html">Mailing list</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/pm/?group_id=76468">Task list</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=76468&amp;atid=547191">Bug tracker</a></li>
</ul>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p class='q'>What is it?</p>

<p>
The Zero Install system makes software installation not merely
easy, but unnecessary. Users run their applications directly from the
Internet from the software author's pages. Caching makes this as fast
as running a normal application after the first time, and allows
off-line use.
</p>

<p class='q'>Show me an example.</p>

<p>
Let's say you're looking for a little desktop reminder application. You
search <a href="http://freshmeat.net">Freshmeat.net</a> and find
<a href="http://rox.sf.net/memo.html">Memo</a>. You open the directory
containing Memo (on the remote machine) with your file manager (note the
title-bar):
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="443" height="199" src="apps.png"
     alt='ROX-Filer window showing Memo application on the remote machine' />
</p>

<p>
Click on Memo to run it, and it will run. Now, Memo depends on ROX-Lib2,
which requires pygtk, which needs python2.2 and GTK+-2, which needs glib,
pango and AKT. But that's OK; Memo runs everything it
needs directly from the remote machines where they're stored:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img src='progress.png' width='565' height='235'
     alt='GUI progress indicator' />
</p>

<p>
When you ran Memo, a progress indicator appeared briefly, showing the download
progress. If you quit Memo and run it again, it will start instantly, because
the Zero Install system has cached everything locally.
</p>

<p>
Note that the progress display and downloading are <i>not</i> performed by the
file manager; the filer sees this as an ordinary directory. The Zero Install
system automatically cached the remote resources when they were accessed. You
could have run Memo from a shell prompt, and it would have worked just as well.
</p>

<div class='note' style='text-align: left'><h3>Key points</h3>
<ul>
<li>Software is only ever <i>cached</i>, not <i>installed</i>. Anyone can run
any software, and nothing is run as root.</li>
<li>Running a program is done in the same way whether it's cached or not.</li>
<li>Running cached software is as fast as running traditionally-installed
software.</li>
<li>Zero Install is both simpler and more secure than traditional packaging
systems.</li>
<li>Software can be removed from the cache to free space without affecting
the behaviour of the system (it will be recached on demand).</li>
</ul>
</div>

<p class='q'>What about package management systems like APT?</p>

<p>
These require a central authority to maintain the database. For example, you
can't install Memo using APT, because Debian don't package it. The best an
author can do is provide Debian .deb packages on the site. But then the user
still has to do the manual dependency resolution above for everything not in
Debian's system.
</p><p>
They are also fragile; if the user deletes managed files then
the system may stop working. However, a user can remove any part of the
Zero Install cache at any time, and it will simply be fetched again if it's
needed later.
</p><p>
Also, a user installing from a .deb, .rpm, etc still has to enter the root
password and run a script as root. This is inconvenient and a security risk.
Zero Install allows users to run software without root privileges.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href="compare.html">comparison with other systems</a> document
for a more detailed list of the advantages of Zero Install.
</p>

<p class='q'>Isn't running stuff off the net a security risk?</p>

<p>Isn't that where you get your software from anyway? Zero Install
automatically performs a number of checks for you (such as checking MD5 sums
and GPG signatures), and since it doesn't run any of the remote code as root,
you can try software out safely as a 'guest' user. Once downloaded, the
programs are run from the cache, without even checking the original sites for
updates (you have to tell it to update manually).
</p>

<p>See the <a href="security.html">security model</a> document for more
information about security in Zero Install.</p>

<p class='q'>Can I try it out?</p>

<p>
Although the system makes installing other software very easy, the Zero
Install system itself still requires some work to install. Please read this:
</p>
<ul>
<li> <a href="install.html">Step-by-step installation walk-though</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p class='q'>Is it fully working yet?</p>

<p>It's still under development, but the examples given here already
work. You can run Memo as shown above, and it will get ROX-Lib and pygtk via
Zero Install. However, the other libraries are not yet in Zero Install, so you
will need to install Gtk, etc, as normal for now.
</p>

<p>
Take a look at our <a href="http://sourceforge.net/pm/?group_id=76468">tasks
list</a> for a list of things being worked on (or things that will be worked
on when we get volunteers). We really need lots of volunteers to start packaging
some common libraries for other things to depend on...
</p>

<p class='q'>Do I have to enter the full URI every time I want to run a
program?</p>

<p>No, create a shortcut to it instead. For example, you could drag Memo
from the window above onto a panel or the desktop background, or set it to load
when you log in. You can assign a keyboard shortcut to an application, add it
to the Send To menu, bookmark it, stick it on a `Start' menu, put it in PATH,
make a shell alias or use any other normal method of making something easier to
get to.
</p>

<p class='q'>I have more questions!</p>

<p>Try <a href="faq.html">the FAQ</a>.</p>

<p>More technical readers might want to read the
<a href="technical.html">technical details</a> page.
</p>

<h3>Articles about Zero Install</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://freshmeat.net/articles/view/1049/">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (freshmeat editorial and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=5394">Zero Install and the Web of Software</a> (OSnews article and comments)</li>
<li><a href="http://slashdot.org/~Sanity/journal/47655">Package Management in the untimate operating system</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ed.puddingbowl.org/archives/001198.html">Ed Heil's Weblog</a></li>
</ul>


</html>
