<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">

<h2>The Injector</h2>

<p>
A running process is created by combining many different libraries (and other components).
In the Zero Install world, we have all versions of each library available at
all times. The problem then is how to choose which versions to use.
</p>

<p>
The injector solves this problem by selecting components to meet a program's requirements,
according to a policy you give it. The injector finds out which versions are available,
and downloads and runs the ones you choose:
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img width="545" height="325" src="edit-injector.png"
     alt="Running Edit with the injector" />
</p>

<div class='note'>
Note: The injector is pure Python. You do <b>not</b> need the rest of Zero
Install. No extra kernel modules required!
</div>

<h2>Installing the injector</h2>

<p>
To use the injector, you will need:
</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://python.org">Python</a> (version 2.3 or later, <i>including</i> any <b>-dev</b> package).</li>
<li><a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GnuPG</a> (to check the digital signatures).</li>
<li><a href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/pygtk/?branch_id=12503">PyGTK 2.4 or later</a> (only needed for the GUI).</li>
<li><a href="http://0install.net/public_key.gpg">My GPG key</a>. You can download and import
it with:
<pre>
$ gpg --recv-key --keyserver www.keyserver.net 59A53CC1
</pre>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Note that the injector works without needing the Zero Install filesystem to be
installed (you can think of it as the next version of Zero Install).
</p>

<p>
Download the injector from <a
href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=76468&amp;package_id=146899">the
download page</a>, or using wget:
</p>
<pre>
$ <b>wget http://osdn.dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/zero-install/injector-0.8.tar.gz.gpg</b>
</pre>

<p>
Check that the signature is correct using GPG. This also ensures that you have my key installed, which
you will need later!
</p>

<pre>
$ <b>gpg injector-0.8.tar.gz.gpg</b>
gpg: Signature made Fri 13 May 2005 20:44:57 BST using DSA key ID 59A53CC1
gpg: Good signature from "Thomas Leonard &lt;XXXXX@users.sourceforge.net&gt;"
gpg: WARNING: This key is not certified with a trusted signature!
gpg:          There is no indication that the signature belongs to the owner.
Primary key fingerprint: 9242 9807 C985 3C07 44A6  8B9A AE07 8280 59A5 3CC1
</pre>

<p>
The warning is just to tell you that you haven't yet established that the key really
belongs to me (ultra-paranoid users will now cross-check the finger-print using
some other source of information).
</p>

<p>
You should now extract the archive, and change directory inside it:
</p>
<pre>
$ <b>tar xzf injector-0.8.tar.gz</b>
$ <b>cd injector-0.8</b>
</pre>

<table>
 <col id="col1"/>
 <tr><th>Installing normally</th><th>Installing without root access</th></tr>
 <tr>
  <td>
  <p>For a normal install, su to root, install, and exit from root:</p>
<pre>$ <b>su</b>
[ enter root password ]
# <b>python setup.py install</b>
# <b>exit</b>
</pre>
 </td><td>
<p>
If you don't have the root password, use this command.
You'll need to make sure that ~/bin is in $PATH in this case.
</p>
<pre>$ <b>python setup.py install --home ~</b></pre>
  </td>
 </tr>
</table>

<p>
You now have two new commands: <b>0launch</b>, which takes the URL of a program and runs it, and
<b>0alias</b>, which lets you use short names instead of URLs.
</p>

<p>
Now it's time to <a href='injector-using.html'>try using it</a>!
</p>

</html>
