<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<h2>Zero Install security overview</h2>

<p>
This page discusses some of the security issues relating to Zero Install.
</p>

<p>
The key idea behind making secure systems is always the same: make a small
and trusted 'core' system, and make sure that the rest of the system can grow
without introducing additional security problems.
</p>

<h3>System security key points (design)</h3>
<ul>
<li>No downloaded software is ever run as root, or as any user except the one
who asked to run it.</li>
<li>The system is fully protected from software users 'install'.</li>
<li>Users are fully protected from each other.</li>
<li>Zero Install performs checks to try to detect when a remote server has
been compromised. This only works when upgrading software, not when using it
for the first time.</li>
</ul>

<h3>System security key points (implementation)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Zero Install contains a very small kernel module, which is the only
(new) vector for a possible root-compromise.</li>
<li>A smaller helper runs as a separate user. If compromised, it would
allow trojaning of software run via Zero Install, but not of the system
itself.</li>
<li>Zero Install does not listen for incoming connections (any attack
must be initiated by a local user, intentionally or otherwise).</li>
</ul>

<h3>User security key points</h3>
<ul>
<li>Anyone can run any software they please, without endangering anyone
but themselves.</li>
<li>A user running a malicious program can still lose their own data, but
Zero Install makes it easier to use other techniques to solve this separate
problem.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Security on Unix-type systems</h2>

<p>
On Unix-type systems, such as Linux, each piece of software runs with a
particular 'user ID' (UID). The kernel ensures that a piece of software running
with one UID cannot interfere with another piece of software running with a
different one. Typically, each person who uses the computer has a
corresponding UID, and each system process (such as booting or serving web
pages) has its own one too. Thus, I can't accidentally delete someone else's
files, or prevent the computer from booting in future, since running as
a different UID requires a password.
</p>

<p style='text-align: center'>
<img src="Users.png" width='475' height='421' alt='Linux protects users from each other'/>
</p>

<p>
In fact, UID 0 ('root') is special. Programs running as root can do anything
they like, including messing with other user's files and programs and even
changing Linux itself. Therefore, we try to run as little software
as possible as root.
</p>

<h2>Zero Install security in detail</h2>

<h3>Installing as different users</h3>

<p>
Debian's approach to security (which is typical) is to only allow you to
install their 'trusted' packages. Each package contains an installer program
which is run as 'root' when the package is installed, uninstalled or upgraded.
Clearly, Debian cannot allow users to install arbitrary packages while using
this system; the user could install a package with a malicious install program.
Once packages are installed, however, the programs they contain are run only as
normal users. Tarballs and RPMs are typically installed in a similar fashion.
</p>

<p>
Zero Install separates installation from trust: only the (small) Zero Install
system itself must be audited for correctness and security. When a package
is 'installed' using Zero Install, none of the code within the package is
run at all, it is simply copied from the remote machine to a local disk cache
(for speed reasons).
If Zero Install is secure, any other software may be installed and upgraded
using it without risking the system. Trust in the software is only needed when
the software is run, and only the user running the software needs to trust it.
</p>

<p>
For example, if Mary (in the picture above) wanted to install KWord on a Debian
system, she would need to ask the system administrator for permission, because
a bug or exploit in KWord's installer could delete John's files. This is
both inconvenient (having to find the administrator) and still a risk (bugs
may still slip through).
</p>

<p>
Mary could install KWord herself, without running it as root, but then only
she could use it. If John decided to run KWord too, he would have to
download a second copy, wasting time and disk space. Of course, he could
use Mary's copy, but this has two problems:
</p>

<ul>
<li><p>John has to know that Mary (or some other user) has installed it, and
she has to have made it accessible to him.</p>
</li>

<li><p>
John has to trust not only Mary herself, but any program she runs now or
in the future. Any program running with Mary's UID can modify her copy of
KWord, which John is also using. Thus, by running Mary's copy of KWord, John
is giving Mary access to all his files (and, by extension, to all the files
of everyone who trusts software John has installed, and so on).</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
The Zero Install system has its own UID. It acts like a very trust-worthy
version of Mary, downloading software for other people, but never actually
<i>running</i> anything. Since none of the downloaded software runs with
the Zero Install UID, the software can't be changed.
</p>

<h3>Trusting software on the web</h3>

<p>
So Zero Install moves the issue of trust on to individual users. Instead of
the Debian model, where the administrator only installs trusted software and
all users trust the administrator's judgement, any piece of software can be
'installed', but users must decide whether they want to run it.
</p>

<p>
Zero Install can do this, because users specify some software to run by its URI
(Internet address). There is no question of a user asking to run 'gimp' and
having to decide which program named 'gimp' they mean; they explicitly ask for
'http://www.gimp.org/gimp-1.2' (though, as explained elsewhere, the user
interface may not present it quite like this).
</p>

<p>
This brings up two questions:
</p>

<ul>
<li>How does a user know what sources of software on the Internet are
trust-worthy?</li>
<li>How does Zero Install know that the software came from where it says
it does?</li>
</ul>

<p>
The answer to the first question is that you still need some kind of
recommendation system. In Debian's case, this is tied up with the installer:
what Debian recommend can be installed; what they don't, can't. In Zero
Install, sites such as <a href="http://freshmeat.net">freshmeat.net</a>,
or distributions, take on this responsibility. A user of Zero Install may
choose, for example, to only run programs listed on Debian's web-site.
However, they may also choose to trust a magazine, a friend or some other
source.
</p>

<p>
The second question is more technical. Since software is named by its
Internet address, Zero Install simply fetches it from that, just as a web
browser does with a named web page. However, there are some issues with this:
</p>

<ul>
<li><p>To speed things up, we may choose to get the software from a mirror
(a computer with a copy of the program which happens to be closer to us).
Can we trust the mirror?</p></li>

<li><p>The computer serving the software could have been broken into, and the
software replaced with a trojaned version.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>
To solve the mirror problem, Zero Install creates index files which list
every file available from the site, alternative download locations for the
files, and checksums for each group of files. The (small) index file comes from
the master site, but the data can come from anywhere. When the data arrives,
the checksum (MD5) is calculated and compared to the one in the index. If they
differ, the download is refused. So, it is only necessary to ensure that the
index files are authentic. (MD5 is a popular checksum algorithm designed for
exactly this purpose; it is infeasible to find a way of changing the archive
while preserving the checksum)
</p>

<p>
For the index files themselves, we use a different system. Zero Install
actually downloads three files: the index, the site's public key, and
the index's digital signature. It confirms that the signature was created
using the private key corresponding to the downloaded public key, and that
the signature is a checksum of the index file (see the
<a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GNU Privacy Guard</a> homepage for an
explanation of how all this is possible).
</p>

<p>
This may not seem to buy us anything (an attacker could change all three files
at once), but the advantage is that when we <i>upgrade</i> the software
(by fetching an updated index file) we check the new index and signature
using the <i>original</i> key. Thus, if an attacker does change the files
on the server, the next person to try to update will be shown a big scary
message telling them to warn the site owner, and the problem can be fixed
quickly.
</p>

<p>
In other words, Zero Install doesn't check that the software is written by
who it says it is, and it doesn't check that they're trust-worthy, but it
<i>can</i> tell you that an upgrade for a piece of software you've found to be
trust-worthy in the past is from the same people as before.
</p>

<h3>Extra security from distributions</h3>

<p>
Distributions or other groups can provide extra security by distributing
sites' public keys themselves. The RedHat installer might pre-install the file
<tt>/var/cache/zero-inst/gimp.org/.0inst-key.pub</tt>, even if they didn't
supply the Gimp itself. Other groups can provide a similar service; since
they system will only work if both the key provider and the software provider
use the same key, the worst that malicious key providers can do is to prevent
genuine software from installing (but can't install malicious software
themselves).
</p>

<p>
Distributions can also provide users with notification and key-update
services, allowing RedHat, for example, to prevent their users from
running software from a particular cracked site until the issue is resolved
(to protect users who've never accessed the site before, or in the extreme
case that the site's secret key has been compromised).
</p>

<h3>Protecting users from themselves</h3>

<p>
What if a user wants to try some software, but doesn't fully trust it? Zero
Install will protect the rest of the system from that user, but not the user
from himself. However, users have a number of options independent of Zero
Install for running software in safety.
</p>

<p>
First, there are tools such as <a
href="http://subterfugue.org/">Subterfugue</a>, which can intercept all system
calls made by a process and block or change destructive ones. For example, a
user could run a program but only allow it to write to their ~/Testing
directory.
</p>

<p>
Secondly, <a href="http://user-mode-linux.sf.net">User Mode Linux</a> allows
any user to run a whole Linux system within Linux. Normally, this rather
restricts the amount of software available, but with Zero Install they can
mount /uri within the virtual machine as a hostfs type mount of the real
machine's /uri directly, thus sharing all downloads between both the real
and virtual machines. Any changes made will only affect the virtual machine.
</p>

<p>
Third, and perhaps simplest, the system administrator can create a 'sandbox'
UID for testing software. Any user can log in as 'testing' and try programs
out, safe in the knowledge that no important data is saved as that UID.
</p>

<h3>Trusting Zero Install itself</h3>

<p>
As we have seen, the security of the whole computer system only depends on the
security of Zero Install itself, which is fairly small and comparatively easily
audited.  In this section, we consider what attacks are possible due to bugs
here.
</p>

<p>
The first and most important point to understand is that <strong>Zero Install
is experimental software</strong>. Since it is still rapidly changing, it has
not yet been carefully checked for correctness, and should not be used anywhere
where that could cause problems.
</p>

<p>
There are various types of exploit that can be launched against a computer
system. A <strong>local exploit</strong> is where one of the users of the
computer gets access to something they shouldn't (such as the ability to
modify another user's files). A <strong>remote exploit</strong> allows
someone elsewhere on the Internet to get access to the machine.
</p>

<p>
Systems which offer a service (such as a serving web pages) to the outside
world may allow remote exploits if buggy. You could set up a web server, go on
holiday for a week, and return to find the machine compromised. Zero Install
does not listen for incoming connections, so this kind of attack is not
possible. Zero Install only talks to other machines at the request of a user
on the computer itself.
</p>

<p>
Therefore, there are three ways in which a buggy Zero Install could be
exploited:
</p>

<ol>
<li>A local user of the machine attacks it.</li>
<li>A local user is tricked into running software from a dodgy site, and this
software exploits a bug in Zero Install to get access to the rest of the system.</li>
<li>A local user accesses a trusted site which has been broken in to.</li>
</ol>

<p>Point 3 is the same as point 2, except that Zero Install can detect the
problem if the site has been accessed in the past (due to the use of digital
signatures described above).</p>

<p>
Before anyone gets too paranoid, please remember that existing systems require
you to trust <strong>all</strong> downloaded programs (hundreds or thousands
of them), whereas Zero Install is just one program.
</p>

<p>
Since Zero Install runs with its own UID, even if compromised it should not
stop the system from booting or interfere with core system services. It would,
however, allow the attacker to trojan all software available via Zero Install.
If both the Zero Install program <strong>and</strong> the kernel module
contained exploits, the attacker could get control of the whole machine.
However, this would require an extremely skillful attacker, and three
separate vulnerabilities (tricking a local user, getting past the downloader
program, and getting past the kernel module).
</p>

<p>
However, since Zero Install is small and will be infrequently changing, any
bugs found can be quickly corrected and new bugs should be very rare. After
the 1.0 release, hopefully many programmers will help us check it.
</p>

<h3>Future security possibilities</h3>

<p>
Zero Install moves security threats from system-wide to per-user; a big
step forward. However, it may also make possible future security improvements,
too. We can imagine that when running a program it should not get write
access to the filesystem at all (even as the user who ran it). Dragging a
private file to a word processor could give it permission to read it, and
dragging the file back to the filer could grant it write permission to save
it.
</p>

<p>
This would finally allow users to run random email attachments and other
untrusted programs they find lying around in safety. However, there is the
problem of preferences. OpenOffice should be able to save user preferences
and a list of recently edited documents without having to ask the user
for permission. Zero Install makes this easy; when the user runs
`.../openoffice.org/writer' in the filer, the filer could automatically grant it
write permission on `~/.config/openoffice.org', without any risk that it
could mess up another application's preferences.
</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>
We have seen that Zero Install can provide a much more secure environment
that traditional systems. Because every resource a program may ever require
is already at a fixed location in the file system, there is no need for
installers to move things around and update index files recording what is
available on the system. By removing the need for complex installers, we remove
the need to run untrusted code with system-level privileges. In this safer
environment, we can allow users to run whatever software they require,
allowing us to create a system that is both simpler and safer.
</p>

<p>
This creates a system where only individual user accounts can be compromised.
We can now create a `guest' user to safely test out new software, or a
`backup' UID to keep copies (regular off-site backups are still required to
guard against hardware failures, of course).
</p>

<p>
By separating installation from trust, we allow better recommendation services
to appear. By automatically checking GPG signatures as software is upgraded,
we are able to perform better security checking than the majority of users
currently do, with no extra effort.
</p>

<p>
Having a URI-based naming scheme, shared by all platforms and distributions,
we can share a single Zero Install downloader among any number of virtual
machines, making running `sand-boxed' applications much easier. By referring
to each application by it's full URI, we can grant an application write access
to it's own private configuration area with no additional user interaction.
</p>

<p>
Although the Zero Install system is not finished, and still requires auditing
itself, this document has hopefully served to suggest that the final system
will be a considerable improvement on current systems, not just in
user-friendliness, but in security too.
</p>

</html>
